ZachCalvert@Gmail.com
https://www.linkedin.com/in/zachcalvert

Enterprise Cloud Architect

SUMMARY

Skilled Software Engineer focused in cloud migrations applying enterprise architecture patterns with a DevOps approach. Full-stack aware, trained in both ReactJS and Angular, with 15 years Java experience currently building 12-factor applications using Spring Boot Microservices. Active in applying Agile Methodologies, and DevOps CI/CD. Hands on experience with Linux server diagnostics, cloud server virtualization, and monolithic decompositions.

PROFICIENCIES

Cloud Engineering - 4 years

Pivotal Cloud Foundry, OpenShift, Kubernetes, AWS, Event Driven Design, CQRS, Open API 3.0, Docker, 12 Factor Applications, Eventual Consistency *Java - 15 years*

Spring Boot Microservices, Hibernate, Camel, JUnit, JMockit, Gradle, OSGi, JDBC, ServiceMix, Maven, Groovy, Spock

DevOps - 8 years

Cloud Formation, Jenkins, Travis CI, Vagrant, Ansible, Heroku, Bamboo, CI/CD JavaScript - 7 years

ReactJS, Angular, NPM, Bootstrap 4, ES6, Chai, Jasmine, JQuery

NoSQL - 4 years

Cassandra, Redis, MongoDB

Eventing Systems - 8 years

Kafka, RabbitMQ, ActiveMQ, Tibco

SQL - 15 years

Oracle, MySQL, PostgreSQL, MS SQL Server

Atlassian Development Services - 8 years

Jira, BitBucket, Bamboo, Confluence, FishEye

Linux - 15 years

Server management, bash scripting, installation, performance monitoring

Development Toolkits - 15 years

Git, IntelliJ, Eclipse, Gradle, Maven, Subversion, Ant

Security Mitigation - 9 years

TLS, WireShark, salted hashing, encryption, Bcrypt, BouncyCastle

Server Clustering, Scaling, and Disaster Recovery - 8 years

Disaster Recovery Planning, Chaos Monkey, Geo-redundancy, recovery analysis Performance Testing - 10 years

JMeter, Artillery, Thread Dump Analyzer, Garbage Collection Viewer, JConsole

EXPERIENCE

BNSF Railway

Fort Worth, TX February 2017 - current

Contractor for HCL on-site at BNSF Railway serving as Enterprise Cloud Architect on the train service modernization Platform Team. Our team responsibilities are to identify the appropriate stack of technologies for a successful migration to a modern microservice architecture for train scheduling and staff management.

Private Key Material Management 6 Months, SAFe Agile
Served as OpenShift solutions architect and technical lead for the BNSF Enterprise
Security team working on private key material management. Focus on DevOps
integration and automation for securing sensitive event topics and 12-factor
application TLS exposure. Full automation of authentication issuance via mTLS
for internal service-to-service with signed JWT for users and external customers.

Microservice API Production Monitoring 4 Months, SAFe Agile Served as Product Owner and Technical Lead for identifying applicable toolkits supporting OpenShift and Kubernetes monitoring. Performed requirement gathering and stakeholder identification ranging from technical staff to business leadership. Evaluations included Dynatrace, App Dynamics, New Relic, Nagios, Graphite/Grafana, and ELK.

Securing REST and Identity Management 5 Months, SAFe Agile
Provide stateless components and integration suite for migration to a modern JWT based identity solution. Integration components built for migrating existing stateless SOAP and REST APIs, Spring Boot microservices, service-to-service application communication, and JSF/JSP WAR legacy applications. Full support for native mobile IOS and Android applications.

BlueMix and Cloud Foundry Evaluation 3 months, SAFe Agile
Evaluate the enterprise readiness for IBM BlueMix with integration to Jenkins
CI/CD pipelines for private cloud migration. Prepare best practice outlines and
documentation for adopting Cloud Foundry command line utilities, configuration
management, and deployment architecture.

Cache Service Evaluations

3 months, SAFe Agile

Served as technical lead evaluating cache offerings for Java applications to support J2EE migrations to OpenShift. Evaluations included Reddis, Caffeine, Infinispan, JBoss Data Grid, Ehcache, Hazelcast, and Memcached.

Spireon

Irving, TX

July 2016 - February 2017

Joined a Spring Boot Microservice REST API software team developing, testing, and reviewing security for services deployed on Amazon AWS as a Senior Software Engineer.

JWT Identity Management

3 Months, Agile

RESTful security transition to JWT identity services served via a Tyk Gateway and nginx reverse proxies. Responsible for implementation of the caching integration to Redis and ehCache on a Java 8 Spring Boot microservice, with a JPA based MySQL integration. Personally achieved 80% unit testing coverage of both lines and branches with cobertura code coverage delivered via Jenkins CI builds. Implemented CXF REST services. Localized authentication and principal managed via Spring Security. Performance tested using the NodeJS Artillery module.

Platform API

3 months, Agile

RESTful service managing vehicle asset exposure and geo-locational data. Responsible for reviewing the existing elasticsearch integration, improving search behavior, and providing business logic testing to available searches. Improved both unit testing code coverage, negative test case coverage, and security testing using Frisby and JUnit 4. Aided in improving the gradle build process and improving Jenkins CI builds and automated integration testing.

TEKsystems

Dallas, TX

March 2016 - July 2016

Contractor for TEKsystems as Java Technical Lead at Southwest Airlines HQ serving a team of developers managing a passenger data service which exposes Oracle persisted content via SOAP APIs and updates the same data warehouse via consuming messages off of a bridged Tibco Message Queue built on JMS.

Python Automation Initiative

3 Months, Iterative

Personally recognized an opportunity to improve speed of delivery and reduce manual error with automation of an internal deployment process. Using Python, an error prone deployment involving manual HTML form submission reduced team's involvement by 35 man -hours per week.

PDS Retirement

3 Months, Waterfall

Participated as technical lead of support staff to aid in monitoring of a migration and retirement of an XML warehouse.

Xpressdocs

Fort Worth, TX July 2015 - March 2016

Joined a print firm delivering integration solutions to digital print equipment for real estate marketing, business cards, and advertising campaigns.

JDserv

6 Months, Iterative

Responsible for assisting the migration of a team from waterfall development to Agile Methodologies. Provided development leadership in updating products from Java 6 to Java 8, Ant to Maven, develop CI and CD Jenkins builds, work with IT to deliver JMX monitoring touch points, and aid in developing a Jira workflows.

MelissaData Smart Mover

1 Month, Waterfall

Independently developed an integration service that provided a 750% performance improvement in CASS and NCOA address validations using a producer/consumer design pattern over REST API. Provided a JAR artifact deliverable with 97% code coverage and end-to-end integration tests against a public sandbox test service.

Alcatel-Lucent, Contractor Austin, TX *June 2009 - April 2015* Provided software contracting services for the telecommunication industry including endpoint management, mobile services, and electric smart metering network solutions.

Mobile Push Services

4 Months, Agile Project

Designed and implemented integration services for notifying mobile customers of service outages based on network diagnostics and manual batch notifications. Integrations provided for both Google Cloud Messaging and Apple Push Notification Service. Responsibilities included architecture, implementation, unit testing, performance testing, integration testing, and installation scripting for Linux servers.

Smart Device OSGi Services

24 Months, Agile Project

Designed and implemented REST API services for mobile and browser based applications allowing us to reach new customer bases, including the electric smart metering device market. Responsible for server implementation, requirement gathering, performance testing, security testing, Linux installs, and service design.

Endpoint Communication System

6 Months, Agile Project

Designed and developed Spring-DM OSGi Apache ServiceMix bundles for a push notification architecture supporting PC, Mac, and mobile platforms expanding client installations by hundreds of thousands of units. Responsibilities included server design, implementation, unit testing and directing remote test staff for QA testing and performance testing.

Client Application Framework

15 Months, Agile Project

Developed a PC solution for an application store built on top of OpenJDK and the Apache Felix OSGi stack. Responsibilities included implementation of a locally installed Jetty client service for accessing PC help flows and account management.

Broadband Care Manager

6 Months, Agile Project

Provided support in moving the legacy EAR project suite from manually built to a robust Maven build system centered upon a subversion repository with Atlassian build and project management tools. Improved in-house Eclipse RCP workflow utility and reduced user installation errors with a newly developed NSIS installer.

TransUnion

Austin, TX

Jan 2005 - April 2009

Developed flood research solutions as well as automated home valuation software for real estate and credit reporting industries.

Hornet

12 Months, Iterative

Improved automation output by a factor of 5,000 reducing hardware cost and improving customer feedback with faster turnaround for batch requests. Major factors contributing to the improvement included a new geospatial indexing architecture, custom RAM management, and multi-threading techniques.

Hard Rain

24 Months, Iterative

Developed a flood research application integrating many different data providers into an Eclipse RCP (OSGi) based application. Provided map synchronization and various research and geospatial toolsets to achieve pinpoint accuracy for floodplain identification.

EDUCATION

University of Texas at Arlington

Jan 2000 - Dec 2004

Graduated summa cum laude with a Bachelor of Science in Software Engineering

Online Courseware

Udemy: AWS Certified Developer - Associate 2019

Udemy: AWS Serverless APIs & Apps - A Complete Introduction

Udemy: Docker Mastery: The Complete Toolset From a Docker Captain

Udemy: JavaScript: Understanding the Weird Parts

Udemy: Vim Masterclass

Udemy: Learn DevOps: Infrastructure Automation with Terraform

Udemy: Learn DevOps: The Complete Kubernetes Course

Udemy: Getting Started with Apache Cassandra

Mongo University: MongoDB for Java: 101